Hello, everyone, and
welcome to our penultimate
lecture in our series of
talks on renal physiology.
And today we'll be talking
about the transports
of acids and bases and
start giving you the
preparation into understanding
acid-base disorders
and how to approach them
and what can cause them.
So, like in the previous
cases, we'll start off
with a little scenario.
In this case, think of
yourself on your winter
break and you wanted to,
you're a skier, you
are an avid skier who's
only skied in New York
and you want to go
over and experience real
mountains. So you and
your friend go and you
decide to go ski in
the Rockies and Aspen.
You land in Denver,
a mile-high city, right,
5,280 feet and then
drive to Aspen, which
is a, you know, toward
three hour drive to
the continental divide.
As you get closer to
Aspen, you start getting
headachy and you feel,
you don't feel great, you
start feeling lightheaded.
So you take ibuprofen
and everything is fine,
but then the next day you
are, feel horrible and
gets worse as you take the
lift to the top of your
first run. You have a
horrible headache, you're
nauseous, you're short of
breath, and you can
barely see, you can barely
focus going down the
slope. Your friend is fine.
And once you get down
down the slope, you ask,
you know, like, I'm dying.
What are you, what's going
on? Why do you feel so
good? And she says, well, I'm
taking this drug. My doctor
gave it to me. It was
like, I'd never heard of it
before, but it's like the
greatest drug in the world,
and it's cheap, and it
works so well and you wonder
what's going on with you
and you know what in god's
name is your friend's pill
that she's taking uh so
yeah so denver's at 5 280
feet mile high and aspen's
like almost 3 000 feet higher
than that if you compare
that to the highest
mountain in the catskills um
yeah hunter mountain
which if you're familiar
if you're you know if you
go skiing you probably
you have been there,
it's half as high as
you would see from sea
level for the naspen.
So high altitude is doing
something that causes
headache, fatigue,
shortness of breath, and
mystery drug seems
to be working there.
So these are our objectives.
We're talking about
major sources of acids
and bases in the body,
the processes that give
them the fundamental of
acid-base balances, the
relative roles of the
various segments of the
tubule of the nephron,
and the major regulatory
and variables that are
involved in renal processing
of acids and base.
So we'll start off again
with the big picture.
So here we have the acid-base
balance and distribution
in our body.
Any acid in our diet is
quickly absorbed, and what's
not absorbed is neutralized
once it gets past the
stomach into the intestines
and finally excreted.
The absorbed amount is
found in the exocellular
fluid, and there it
interacts with one of our
major buffers, bicarbonate,
and the bicarbonate
is not only filtered, but
completely reabsorbed.
Additionally, we have
de novo bicarbonate
production in the kidney
that becomes important.
The majority of
work that happens in
regulating, in getting rid of
of the acids is via CO2
through our lungs. So
breathing it out becomes
incredibly important.
But acids and bases
fall into different
categories, and different
organs will have
different effects on the
categories. And we'll
be using this
nomenclature of volatile,
non-volatile acids and
bases. So what is a volatile
acid? I have the definitions
here on the right-hand
side. A volatile acid
is anything, is any acid
derived directly from the
hydration of CO2. And here,
you know, this is CO2,
this is water, so you're
hydrating it, and that
gives you carbonic acid. And
carbonic acid immediately
dissociates into its base and
its acid form and the base
is the major buffer that
is found in the body. We
have other non-volatile
acids also called titratable
acids and some of you
are wincing because you
thought to yourself the last
time I heard the word
titrate was freshman year
chemistry lab and how many
drops of blah blah blah. I don't
know if you remember that.
I have to remember it
to this day of how badly I
screwed that exercise up.
These are acids not
derived from the hydration
of CO2, and the major
one is phosphoric
acid, or in this case,
dihydrogen phosphate.
Phosphoric acid is
H3PO4, but that's
the major non-volatile
titratable acid
we're talking
about. Not the only
one, but that's one
of the major ones.
So the carbon dioxide
bicarbonate system is the
major buffering system in
the body, but we have also
another, the second most
important, the ammonia,
ammonium ion is
the major buffering
system synthesized
in the kidney.
And the kidneys play
an essential role by
neutralizing the non
-volatile acids, the
the phosphates
and the ammoniums.
And, you know, it's so
important that that's one of
the major causes of
consequences of renal failure is
severe acidosis because you're
not, you can't get rid of
your titrate, your titratable
buffer systems and you
accumulate a lot of acid.
So you get severe acidosis.
This table breaks down
the general reactions
that one can, that
finds as the metabolic
source of non-volatile
acids and bases.
So this is volatile, right?
Because it's water and
carbon dioxide. So
reactions producing CO2 from
the oxidation of
carbohydrates and fats, right?
basically everything that
ends up in the Krebs cycle.
Then you have complete
oxidation of neutral amino
acids, gives urea, carbon
dioxide, and water.
Other non-volatile acids,
you get the oxidation
of sulfur-containing
amino acids like the
thionine and cysteine,
which gives you urea,
and sulfuric acid,
which gives us
sulfate ions as a
hydrogen acceptor.
Phosphate-containing
compounds, right?
So many of them, well,
so many proteins that
have phosphates, and you
have to regulate that,
and that gives you the
phosphoric acid system.
Cationic amino acids
like lysine, arginine.
Again, you get urea,
carbon dioxide,
water, and the release
of a proton, and then
you get non-metabolizable
organic acid, like
components of a cramp
cycle or breakdown products
like uric acid, and you
have incomplete oxidation
of carbohydrates in the
past, especially when
it comes to anaerobic
metabolism, where you
get the formation of
lactic acids or keto acids.
Again, in that case,
they'll just dissociate into
their major non-buffering
base and and a proton.
And we have reactions that
can cause non-volatile bases,
and what we're talking
about here, you know,
bicarbonate is non-volatile
base, and you have oxidation
of organic anions like
lactate or oxidation of
anionic amino acids like
spartate and glutamate.
So don't get intimidated
by this. This is just
gives you, I just put
this picture in. You'll
see this picture again
you pulmonary physiology.
But just this goes to
show you where the carbon
dioxide that comes out of
tissues upon metabolism go.
The vast majority of it
will enter red blood cells.
This is where we have all
the hard work being done.
Either it'll bind to
hemoglobin or interact with
hemoglobin, or it gets
metabolized by an enzyme called
carbonic anhydrase to
carbonic acid, which then
immediately dissociates into
protons and bicarbonate,
which comes out of the
cell. This also happens
outside the cell, but the
point is the majority of it,
up to almost 70% is
found as a result
of the activity of this enzyme.
Again, you don't have to
know the absolute, all
the reactions and where they
go. This is just a great
big picture to give you
an idea of what we're
talking about when we talk
about carbon dioxide and
bicarbonate and carbonic acid.
So again, we go back to the
kidney, because the last
time I checked, this is
still talking about the
kidney. We'll have Dr.
LaHesse talk about pulmonary
physiology. So remember,
the lungs excrete the large
amount of potential acid in
the form of CO2. Anything
that affects the lung
and breathing can have
consequences on acid-base
balance, whether it's inherent
pulmonary disorders,
anything to do with smoking,
lung cancer,
anything like, anything
that affects with, with,
with the, with the mechanics
of the lung, or when you
have situations where you
have changes in, or, or
things that affect you,
the breathing centers in
your brain, increasing
cerebrospinal fluid pressure,
you know, opioids, for
example, all affect
respiration rates,
and that can have
a consequence on your
acid-base balance.
And you know, I like this
graph for a couple of
reasons. One, it gives you
an idea of an incredibly
narrow range of arterial
pHs that we need
to keep everything in.
So anywhere between 7.37,
7.42. Anything below 7.37
is alkalemia. Everything
above 7.42 is considered
acidemia. Remember,
acidemia is the state
of being in acidosis.
Acidosis is the process.
But I want you to pay attention
to the y-axis. Look at
the incredibly small amounts
of changes in the proton
concentrations in your
plasma that can affect that.
So this is a nano equivalence,
which for protons, one
equivalence is one millimolar.
So one milliequivalent
is one millimolar. In this
case, one nano equivalence
is one nanomolar. So we're
talking about levels that
are a thousand times below
what we would find normally
in terms of the bicarb in
our blood, because filtered
load is millimolar. So our
capacity to pick up extra
protons is really just much
more than what we need. So
it requires a big effect
to have consequences on pH.
You saw the daily filtered
load in a couple of slides
back and we saw that it was
around 4,300 millimoles,
that's how much we filter.
We reabsorb almost all
of it, but if that bicarb
was left in the urine,
if we couldn't reabsorb all
of it, then that actually
would translate to an
equivalent increase in acidity
in terms of millimolars
in our blood. So that
becomes a blood acid load of
4,300 millimoles. And that's
the same thing as saying
4,300 milliequivalents.
And you can understand
when you see something
like that, that it's
catastrophic metabolic
acidosis. You can see why
it's called catastrophic,
because, again, it's so
many orders of magnitude
more than what a body
is capable of dealing.
Even the 70 millimolar
acid load that's
produced by metabolism,
diet, and intestinal
losses must be balanced
because even then,
70 millimolar is the
difference between
having normal pH,
right, around 40, and
then increasing in
by another, you know,
80, you know, that's even
nanomoles, right? That's
not even millimoles. So
you can see even a 70
nanomolar increase can
cause dramatic acidemia.
And so again, very, you
know, so you need to
tightly titrate those
acid levels, because
if you don't do
that, then the pH of
the urine would be
around 1, 1.3, 1.5.
That's caustic.
That burns, will
damage epithelia and tissues.
Lowest urinary
pH is around 4.4.
That's the pH of coffee.
That is not caustic.
You can pour it on
your skin and you'll
be completely fine.
I wouldn't suggest
that, but you know
what I'm talking about.
So again, it's three orders of
magnitude lower than
what's required to
excrete the 70 millimoles
per day of non-volatile
acids. And the kidney
solves this problem not only
by binding it to non
-volatile acids, but binding
it to ammonia of renal
origin, and that'll act as
a hydrogen acceptor, in
this case, to give you
ammonium ion, and you can
get rid of the ammonium
ion, and then bicarbonate
is one of the major ones,
the major buffer to pick up any
additional protons
in the urine.
So how do we control
that? And we'll start off
with bicarbonate. I start
off with bicarbonate, not
because I think it's
special, it's my personal
opinion. It's editorializing.
I love this system.
I it's, I've always
enjoyed talking about it
and just appreciating
its elegance. So we find
bicarb reabsorbed
in the proximal
convoluted tubule,
distal convoluted tubule,
thick ascending limb, and
majorly collecting duct.
These breakdowns are
probably indicative
of a very, very
high bicarb load.
Low normal bicarb loads,
almost all of the bicarb
is reabsorbed at the level
of the proximal tubule.
But the mechanism that
we'll talk about is
exactly the same regardless
of where we are in the
nephra. This is what
happens in every section.
And we'll start off
here with one. So, all
right, so we filtered,
again, 100% of the filtered
load in the Bowman's
capsule ends up in the
ultrafiltrate. And
the kidney's job is to
get it almost all
back. And it does so
very nicely. And so
what happens? So we,
you know, we, the filtered
load of bicarb will
interact with a proton.
And these protons
are either coming from
inside the cell or are
filtered along with
bicarbonate. And there,
they'll associate to
give you carbonic acid.
And carbonic acid is then
metabolized by a luminal
enzyme, an enzyme that's
found on the brush border of
proximal tubules called
carbonic anhydrase. And carbonic
anhydrase will metabolize
H2CO3 to its individual
components, carbon dioxide
and water. Now, in case
you're wondering why it's
called carbonic anhydrase and
it's catalyzing the breakdown
of carbonic acid, this
enzyme is bidirectional. that
it's equally enzymatically
active on either the
product and the substrate,
and the direction where
you have it is depending on
the concentration of the
product and the substrate.
So in this case, the people
who first named it and
did the work on it were
looking at carbonic acid
breakdown. And carbonic acid
breakdown, it's carbonic
anhydrase, taking water away
from a carbonic acid. So
that gives you carbon dioxide
and water. But the enzymatic
activity can go either
way. So in this case,
bicarbonate is broken down
into carbon dioxide and water.
Carbon dioxide is a
gas, so it's very easily
permeable into the cell, and
that's what happens. You find
it inside the cell, and
there it will interact with
water and then again metabolize
bicarbonic anhydrase,
but in this case a different
carbonic anhydrase.
It is a cytosolic
cytoplasmic, cytosolic
enzymes, ubiquitous. You find
this isoform of carbonic
anhydrase in every cell of
your body. So that's number
five. Then you get, again,
it metabolizes the
formation of carbonic
acid. And then that
dissociates into
bicarbonate and a proton and
the proton is recirculated
back into the lumen where
it can interact with more
filtered bicarb and then
the other bicarb is then
removed and put back into
the interstitium to go back
into the plasma by a sodium
bicarbonate co-transporter.
Now why do this molecule,
and you are spending
almost no energy
reabsorbing all of it.
In fact, the only energy
that's spent is the
energy that the tubular
cells use to create
the gradient which
you need to, you know,
drive sodium in and then
for protons to go out.
So I just find the fact
that evolution has created
a process that doesn't
use any energy and gets
something back. I mean,
this has got to be the
pinnacle of evolution.
It's just really amazing.
Carbonic anhydrase is,
all of them, you know,
all the different isoforms
are inhibitable by a
drug, by a class of
the superfamily of the
sulfonamide class of
drugs called carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors, CAIs.
And the most common
drug is acetazolamide.
So how about non
-bicarbonate buffers?
Well, nine-bicarbonate buffers,
let's first talk
about phosphates,
especially, again,
non-ammonia, non-bicarbonate
buffers, and that
the major one is phosphoric
acid, and in this
case, what's floating
around in the plasma is
monohydrogen phosphate, and
it becomes, you know, and
then creatinine and urate
are some of the other
ones, but the major one
is hydrogen phosphate.
And kidneys excrete hydrogen
-bound phosphates in the
urine. And in this case,
the PCT reabsorbs a fair
amount, and then the thick
ascending limb and the distal
convoluted tubule and the
medullary collecting ducts
also play a component.
You do have a
certain amount of
loss, the urinary
proton loss that's
associated with that.
But the important,
but going back to
how does it work,
is remember, if
you have excess
proton in your lumen,
that'll bind with
monohydrogen phosphate.
And the increases in
acidity, the decrease in
pH, if you remember
when we had our lecture
on transports of potassium,
calcium, magnesium,
and phosphate, that
a decrease in pH will
inactivate some of the sodium
phosphate co-transporters,
and you have less absorption
of H2PO4 and HPO4.
So in this case, what you
end up having is, again,
by virtue of the activity
of carbonic anhydrase, you
get de novo formation of
bicarb. The proton is then
released back into the
lumen where it will bind to
HbO4 to H2, you know, to
dihydrogen phosphate. And
you may lose this in
the urine because the
increase in pH is
inhibiting its reabsorption,
but because you have
a de novo formation
of bicarb, you can
balance out the loss.
And this contributes to
net acid excretion on
three factors. So obviously,
the amount you have
in your filtrate
in the urine, the
filtered load of
monohydrogen phosphate.
The PK is very important.
So to be effective,
these buffers have
to have a certain pK
that's between the pH
of the filtrate and
the pH of the urine,
and almost all these
non-HCO buffers have
that as a chemical
characteristic, and
obviously the most important
one, a contribution
to net acid is the
pH of the urine. So the
lower the urinary pH,
the more protonated
the buffer, the greater
amount of acid that's
excreted with the
buffer, and the greatest
amounts of bicarb
that can be reabsorbed
back into the body.
So the other important
one is the third class
of acceptors for luminal
protons is ammonia
and we have very little
ammonia filtration.
Why? Because we have
very little ammonia.
Plasma ammonia
concentrations are
exceptionally low. If
you have detectable
plasma ammonia,
you have issues.
So the process of
ammonia, ammonium ion, is
the result of five
processes. One secrete, the
proximal convoluted tubules
secrete 40 millimoles
of ammonium ion into
the tubular lumen.
Then the tau reabsorbs
this ammonia and deposits
it into the interstitium.
So here we have that,
right? So ammonia will
go in and then get
reabsorbed into the
interstitium. Now, I want you
to look at this two
-dimensional representation
of the nephron, put a
hinge right over here at
the base, and then turn
this area of the nephron
90 degrees, so the glomeruli
is facing you. Then
you can see the
proximity of the proximal
convoluted tubule to the
tau and their interstitium,
how it can be connected.
So any reabsorption
of tau into the
interstitium results in the
secretion of that ammonia
into the thin descending
limbs, some of it,
obviously not all of it.
The rest of it is still
in the interstitium,
will get secreted into
the collecting duct, and
there it can, in the
interstitium, also get reabsorbed
back into the vasorecta,
and the vasorecta will take
that ammonia away from
the nephron to the general
circulation for it to go
into the liver and get
detoxified. And then you get rid
of anything that was secreted
back into the collecting
duct through the urine.
So a couple of things,
apical membrane of the
towel has got very low
ammonia permeability.
So how does it get into
the cell? It does so by
jumping onto existing
transporters, which
you should be familiar
with by now a little bit,
it starts kicking out
potassium and jumping
in and taking potassium
and getting back into
the cell via the sodium
potassium two chloride
co-transporter. It also
will use the ROMK channel
and kind of jump into,
you know, going
through the membrane,
into the kidney through
the ROMK channel.
What happens there? It'll
divide, it'll dissociate
into ammonium and then
protons. The protons
will then interact
with the reabsorbed
bicarbonate to give you
carbonic acid, and we know
what happens to that.
And then the ammonia is
reabsorbed back into
the interstitium
through some unknown mechanism.
About the medullary collecting
duct, medullary collecting
duct, again, this is the
area that we're thinking
about, right? It's supposed
to go from the interstitial
into the tubule, and
it does so by these two
transporters called gas
channels, and these gas channels
transport ammonium into the
cytosol. If you have any,
you know, there either
it'll get transported into
the lumen by another gas
channel at the apical,
or if there's any de novo
ammonia production in
these cells, they just
dissociate and the proton
gets excreted, while
the NH3 is also removed.
And basically what
you're doing is
you are trying to
get rid of ammonia.
So you're losing it by
diffusion into the lumen.
So you're trying to
minimize the entry of toxic,
of a toxic proton, but
anything that comes back
is very, very quickly
detoxified by the liver.
So in a steady state,
you have some buildup of
NH4 of ammonium ion in
the medulla, And that
actually plays a role in
ability to urine to concentrate.
We'll talk about that
in the next lecture.
Excuse me.
So how do we regulate renal
acid secretion? Well, we
have four major pH
disturbances in our body and a
variety of physiological,
pathophysiological, pharmacological
stimuli can modulate
renal protons and amino
secretion and synthesis.
So I like these graphs. It
shows you our acid base
and what we can see just by
basic laboratory values.
So again, this is where we
want to be. that's the sweet
spot. We want to be at a
pH of 7.4. So if your
respiratory acidosis is when
we have a low pH and high
bicarbonate, metabolic
acidosis is low pH, low
bicarbonate, and then you have a
metabolic alkalosis, just
right on the blue curve
here, where you have a higher
pH and elevated bicarb.
And the exact opposite of
that for respiratory alkalosis
is where you have higher
pH and lower bicarbonate.
And again, your body will
want to bring this back
from the anomalous pH
back to this dotted
line, back to the sweet
spot. You want to be
back at 7.4, regardless
of anything else.
So we have four fundamental
ones. We just talked
about that. Initial
line of defense is to
minimize the magnitude
of the change in pH. You
want to bring it back
as quickly as possible.
And you get compensation from
both the lungs and the kidneys,
or the kidneys, not
necessarily both at the same
time. So let's talk about
respiratory acidosis.
So respiratory acidosis is
when you have the primary
disturbance is when
you have an increase in
arterial, arterial PCA,
CO2, and an increase in
carbon dioxide concentration
in your arterial blood,
not near venous blood,
in your arterial blood.
um if you go back to
that crazy wild picture
i have you can see the
difference i have the
av differences in in
it so you can see how
there is really big
differences so in this case
um what we want to
do we want to get rid
of acid right because
we have acidosis
so our compensatory
response is the production
of de novo bicarbonate
via excretion of ammonia.
And that brings us back closer
to the sweet spot,
our ideal pH,
but not all the way
there. So this is
acute compensation.
You don't get all the
way there, but you
will eventually want to
get there. So the
exact opposite happens
for respiratory
alkalosis, right? It
goes down and then
you want to change.
You are too basic, so you
want to gain acidity, right?
To bring it back to
pH 7.4. So there is an
acute process, brings
you sort of the way
back, and then you have
chronic compensation.
And that chronic
constant, you know,
takes a little bit
longer, and it does
so in three ways,
right? You, one is
you, in proximal tubules,
initially you have an
increase in, the increase in
PCO2 will lead to an
insertion of proton pumps into
the apical membrane, and
you start secreting acid.
Distal tubule, acute
respiratory acidosis, same
process. You get hydrogen
pumps into the apical, you
start pumping acid into
the lumen, right? You have
acidosis, you want to get
rid of it. That's acute.
But chronic, you start
bringing in other players. You
start upregulating the
activity of the sodium proton
exchanger on both the
apical and basolateral sides
and the bicarb exchange co
-transporter in the proximal
tubule. That takes longer,
right? Chronic, the
upregulation of the activities,
you need more of them
and you need more than the
number and whatever regulatory
chemical processes that
act on these to increase
their activity, any kind
of phosphorylation or
transmembrane or membrane
changes, whatever it is, it
takes longer than the immediate
one as a way to compensate
for chronic compensation.
Now you can see like in
the inset and see in
chronic compensation that by
doing that, you bring it
back to 7.3, even though you
have elevated bicarbonate.
That's not as important.
What about metabolic acidosis
in this case, right, acutely?
It stimulates both acid
secretion and ammonia production.
Our first step for acute
metabolic acidosis is a
pulmonary compensation. And
what you do that is you start
breathing, hyperventilating,
increasing alveolar
ventilation. The more you
hyperventilate, the more carbon
dioxide you expire and
that actually corrects the
ratio. And then in the kidney,
you have decreases in bicarb,
and there you have more H
-secretion into the lumen.
Again, the more you have
H-secretion, the more acid
you lose, the faster you can
correct the change in pH.
It also occurs in
distal tubules in the
intercalated cells.
There you have the
hydrogen pump, the
hydrogen ATPase
insertion into the
apical membranes.
Chronic metabolic acidosis,
the responses in the
proximal tubule is the same as
chronic respiratory acidosis,
right? So it's basically
related right up here.
Oops,
that was horrible. I'm
sorry. I'm doing the
mouse, this is not a pen,
so you have to forgive
me when I spazz out
like that. The mouse
doesn't really work
that way. Another very
important one, its
effects on sodium citrate.
And what happens in this
case, you have an increase
in sodium citrate uptake,
and then the citrate gets
metabolized, and then the
increased metabolism of citrate
gives you bicarb, right?
This is what you want. You
want more bicarb to compensate.
However, this loss of
citrate, this decrease
and citrate in the plasma,
citrate is bound, binds to
calcium in extracellular fluid.
So the less citrate you
have, the more free calcium
you have. The more free
calcium you have, you'll get
calciuria, and then you'll
get renal calcium stones.
And that's something that
does happen in chronic
metabolic acidosis. You get
renal calcium stone formation.
And the other compensatory
response is an increase
in ammonium ion excretion.
You get rid of the extra
proton by binding it to
ammonia and getting rid of it.
Metabolic alkalosis, you get
more bicarb in
the plasma, right?
So more bicarb in plasma,
less acid in the plasma,
and therefore you
have less proton efflux
in the proximal tubule.
So what we do is we
switch from luminal
proton secretion to bicarb
secretion. You want to get
rid of more bicarb. So
apical pump and basolateral
chloride bicarb exchanger
insertion into the apical
membranes to get rid of bicarb,
because you kind of want to
get rid of all the extra
stuff that's in the plasma.
In the beta-intercalated
cells, well, a couple of
things. One, you get an increase
in the proportion of the
beta-intercalated cells from
alpha-intercalated cells,
and they have the opposite
apical basolateral distribution
of proton pumps and
chloride bicarb exchangers.
what you end up doing is
getting more bicarbonate
lumen. You have more
bicarbonate lumen,
you urinate and you get
rid of it, and therefore
you can control the
metabolic alkalosis.
Here is a table of the
associated acid-base disorders
compared to normal and
some of our compensation.
This will make more sense
to you once you finish
the pulmonary section.
You can put it all
together a lot easier.
So how is renal acid
secretion regulated? Well,
we have a lot of variables
that can affect renal
acid secretion. We'll go
through them one by one.
So we'll start off by GFR.
Really simple.
GFR is very important. So
if you increase GFR, you
increase bicarb delivery, and
by increasing bicarb delivery,
you enhance reabsorption.
And it's very similar to
sodium balance. I think I've
shown this craft before.
If you just remove the
sodium and it's the bicarb
relationship to filtered
bicarb and reabsorbed bicarb
is identical to filtered
sodium. So this relationship
stays the same. The numbers
may change, you know,
but again it's the
relationship that's important.
So if you have increased bicarb
delivery to the lumen, right,
so the pH in the lumen
goes up and that will
cause an increase in
the sodium hydrogen
exchanger and hydrogen
pumps in the proximal
tubule, which all will
enhance proton secretion.
You increase glomerular
filtration rate, you're
increasing flow, right,
because you're not singularly
just increasing, you're
increasing everything.
This flow can actually
act on a part of
the proximal tubule.
These are an EM of
proximal tube. You can
see the brush border,
and they all have
this central cilium,
right? You can see one
here. You can see another
one here. You can see
a third one here. Every
proximal tubular cell facing
the lumen has got this
one little guy sticking
out, and that central
cilium is a mechanotransducer.
So the more flow
you have, the more bending
you'll have on this
cilium. And the more the
cilium bends, right, like
it's basically like a
wind vein, the greater the
signal to increase the
reabsorption of solutes.
And this glomerular
tubular balance is
very important because
it will minimize
bicarb loss. So
the counter to that
is if you have too high
of a GFR, you can start
losing a lot of bicarb
and you can get metabolic
acidosis. So luminary
tubular balance
of bicarb reabsorption prevents
metabolic alkalosis
when GFR decreases.
So this actually becomes
more of a problem, especially
if you have the surgical
removal of a kidney.
If you have a unifectomy,
that flow has got to
go somewhere, so the flow
increases in the contralateral
kidney, and that will
cause an increase in
the GFR in the remnant
kidney to kind of take it
up in response to the loss
of your renal tissues.
Another big regulator
of renal acid
secretion is
volume contraction.
So if you have a decrease in
exocellular volume, you'll
have an increase in
renin and angiotensin and
sympathetic nervous system
activity. That is a consequence
of the relationship between
volume and pressure. You
have a decrease in blood
pressure. You have a decrease
in blood volume. In almost
all cases, you'll have
a decrease in blood pressure.
That decrease in blood
pressure will activate these
systems, so you'll have
an increase in norepinephrine
and an increase in
angiotensin 2 and aldosterone.
And both in the proximal
tubule, angiotensin 2 and
norepinephrine stimulate sodium
hydrogen exchanger and
enhance sodium reabsorption
and H-secretion. Why is
the sodium reabsorption
important? Well, the body
looks, if you're losing volume,
the body wants to save
volume. By reabsorbing sodium,
what you end up doing
is also water comes
along with it, so increasing
sodium in water is
a way to compensate
for the loss of volume.
In the distal tubule,
angiotensin 2 stimulates acid
secretion by alpha-intercalated
cells, and when you have
chronic volume depletion,
longer term, you start getting
the production of
aldosterone, and aldosterone
enhances proton secretion in
both cortical and medullary
ducts, but that is associated
in changes in potassium.
How about volume expansion
with the exact opposite? Yes,
the exact opposite happens.
Instead of having an
increase in renin and angiotensin
activity, you'll remove
all the renal angiotensin,
and you minimize the
activities, and then you'll
have renal proton retention.
In this context of contraction
and volume expansion,
the body takes precedence in
maintaining volume
and pressure over pH.
That's more, you know,
think about the, you know,
you'll talk about more
of the of the need for
appropriate perfusion and any
kind of a loss in contraction,
you have a loss in
perfusion. pH balance is
the least thing you should
worry about. You start
worrying about renal failure,
obviously too much anoxia,
you'll have damage to
anoxia or any kind of a
lack of flow, you'll have
damage to your central
nervous system, your GI
tract, the barrierification
of the GI tract is very
sensitive to changes in flow.
So any kind of a decrease
in flow can cause the
decrease in barrierification
of your GI tract. So
the whole point is to
maintain the volume regardless
of anything else. So as
a way of prioritizing it,
so this is the
first thing that the
body would think of
is volume over pH.
So hypokalemia is plasma
potassium levels. We talked
about that in our lecture
on potassium, calcium,
magnesium, and phosphate,
right? So hypokalemia
can increase renal
proton secretion, lead
to metabolic acidosis,
alkalosis, excuse me.
And then again, chronically
in proximal tubule, you'll
have an increase in the
sodium proton exchanger
and the sodium bicarbonate
co-transporter. Your urinary
pH will decrease and you
will lose acid, right?
So you get metabolic
alkalosis. And also potassium
depletion can lead to an
increase in ammonia synthesis,
and ammonium ion excretion,
all of them will give you a
loss of protons to give
you a metabolic alkalosis,
including what happens in
the collecting duct. And
hyperkalemia does the exact
opposite, like we talked about
that before, often associated
with metabolic acidosis.
And an increase in
proximal tubule, in the
proximal tubule, an
increase in the pH,
you lower the ammonia
synthesis, you
reduce the excretion
of ammonium ion.
Then you'll have, you can
have competition with any
ammonia in the lumen by
10KCC and ROMK, and that'll
decrease ammonium ion
reabsorption. That'll decrease
ammonia in the medullary
interstitium, and then you'll
have less for diffusion in
the collecting duct. And
of course, increases in
potassium in the medullary
interstitium will compete with
ammonia, again, decreasing
in ammonium ion. All of
it will lead to acidosis.
How about hormones? Well,
hormones will do have an
effect. We talked about
a little bit, but all
the corticosteroids.
Corticosteroids are products
of our adrenal cortex.
Glucocorticoids and
mineralocorticoids stimulate
acid secretion. In fact,
if you have chronic adrenal
insufficiency, people have
Addison's disease, they
get acid retention and they
get metabolic acidosis.
John F. Kennedy, the
assassinated president of the
United States, had Addison's
disease because of excess
cortisol administration
because of a wartime injury,
so he was constantly having
issues with pH balance.
Both glucocorticoids and
mineralocorticoids cause
acid secretion at different
sites of the neuron.
Glucocorticoids, for example,
cortisol increased sodium
proton exchanger, promoting
proton secretion into
the lumen, and hence acidic
urine and loss of protons,
and it decreases phosphate
reabsorption. So that
actually increases luminal
availability for titration.
Mineralocorticoids,
aldosterone. Again, I use
aldosterone as a
mineralocorticoid. We have other
compounds that are in the
pathway of aldosterone synthesis
that have mineralocorticoid
activity. So I really
try to make sure that
the language approach. So
we have other products
of this system that have
mineralocorticoid activity.
But in this case, I'm
just talking about aldosterone
because aldosterone
is the major mineralocorticoid,
but not the only
mineralocorticoid we have
in our body. So we promote
proton secretion directly
in the collecting duct
by increasing the activity
of the proton pump and
then increasing the chloride
bicarbonate exchanger.
It also indirectly increases
proton secretion by
increasing sodium reabsorption
in the collecting duct.
That's the ENAC, right?
So you have more ENAC, you
have more lumen negative
voltage, and that lumen
negative voltage will cause
an increase in H pump in alpha
intercalated cells and
leading to an increase in
acid secretion. And if you
have chronically elevated
aldosterone.
If you are, for example,
if you have heart failure
and you are not getting
treatment for it, eventually
you'll have higher,
you'll have very high
levels of mineralocorticoids
and sodium. If you
put them together, you
can lead to potassium
depletion and indirect
increase in acid secretion.
Mineralocorticoids act in the
mineralocorticoid receptors.
Glucocorticoids can also
act on mineralocorticoid
receptors at high
enough concentrations.
It's a complicated physiology
and biochemistry. Take
my word for it. If not, I
can actually go into gross
detail about how it
works and what the real
relationships are. Just know
that glucocorticoids act on
glucocorticoid receptors and
can act on mineralocorticoid
receptors, while
mineralocorticoid receptors only
act on mineralocorticoid
receptor and have no activity
on the glucocorticoid
receptor. So mineralocorticoid
cannot have any effects on
carbohydrate metabolism,
but excess glucocorticoids
can definitely have
effects on sodium and water
balance. And anybody who's
ever been on a cycle of
glucocorticoids for any
kind of inflammatory issue
can probably address that.
Glucocorticoids can act,
one of the roles
is, I mean, they're
important part of
our armamentarium
for treatment of
various disorders.
But the other class of
agents that can affect
renal acid base are
diuretics. So I have this
table here, breaking down
the different types of
diuretics that one can find,
their targets and where
they act at the nephron,
just as a way to kind of
give you a very, very
brief introduction to them.
As an example of them, so
carbonic anhydrase inhibitors,
right, by virtue of
their name, they act on
carbonic anhydrase. A major
effect is at the proximal
convoluted tubule, but
not exclusively right.
Loop diuretics act on the
thick ascending limb of
the loop of Henle, and
that inhibits the NKCC2
isoform, sodium-potassium
chloride co-transporter.
Distal convoluted tubule is
where you have the thiazides
acting, and that acts on
a different transporter,
sodium chloride co
-transporter, not NKCC, but NCC.
And then you have our
two different types of
potassium sparing
diuretics, the ones that act
on ENAC and the ones
that activate the
mineralocorticoid receptor.
And then you have these
osmotic diuretics
that act on any
kind of a water
permeable segment.
So diuretics fall broadly
in two groups. So you have
ones that promote the
excretion of alkaline urine. So
urinary alkalosis. So
these are the potassium
sparing and carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors.
So obviously, if you
inhibit the carbonic
anhydrase, you decrease
acid secretion, right?
bicarb loss.
So your bicarb levels in
the urine go high, and
the greatest effect is
in the proximal tubule.
And then consequently
you'll have decreases
in acid secretion in
the thick ascending
limb and the distal
convoluted tubule.
For potassium sparing
diuretics, for amylorid and
triamterine, it's nice.
Potassium sparing diuretics is
only four of them. I'm not
using examples. This is the
total number of potassium
sparing diuretics we have.
So amylorid and triamterine
block inhibits this
epithelial sodium channel in
the collecting ENAC. So the
lumen becomes more positive,
and this more positive
disrupts the
electrogenic potential
difference, so proton
secretion is inhibited.
And then spironolactone,
aprelinone is
another on, that
does it directly by
blocking the effects
of aldosterone.
The other two classes of
diuretics that have effects
on renal acid secretion
are loop diuretics and
thiazide diuretics. They act
by volume contraction
and they enhance sodium
delivery to the collecting
duct. You decrease, you
enhance sodium delivery to
the collecting duct, you
increase sodium uptake.
This enhances the lumen
negative voltage and you
promote proton secretion. They
also cause calcium wasting.
One of the major side
effects of lupine thiazides
is hypokalemia, and
this hypokalemia can also
increase proton secretion.
Osmotic diuretics, I
didn't, because it very
much depends on how
they're administered.
People take, you know,
the mannitol and these
osmotic agents are taken,
can be taken orally.
they were used at one
point as laxatives,
as baby laxatives.
They're sweet.
So take it orally, it
doesn't get into your
body. It stays in the
lumen of your GI tract,
absorbing water and
causing stool release.
On IV administration of
mannitol, then
mannitol will get
filtered and not
reabsorbed and cause
massive amounts of water
loss. So the effects
of osmotic diuretics
would be the same
as volume of excessive
volume contraction.
They are very potent diuretics.
So we've gone to the end
of our lecture. So high
altitude, we know that
high altitude will have a
decrease in PO2,
and we have less
PO2, we get less PC, you know,
PaCO2, and our pH in
our blood will go up,
and our urine will
become more alkaline. And
you tell me what that
mystery drug was, but
hopefully you can tell
me that after you have
your lecture with Dr.
Goldstein, and why it's
it's used. Well, thank
you very much, and
I will talk to you
with the next lecture.